Guide to the Susan Howe Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1894-2007; Series II; (7 boxes)
  - Other Writings, 1989-2007
    - Current, 2000 (Box 10)
      Includes printouts, handwritten notes, and other material relating to "Plain Chair or Two Black" and "Scandza".
    - Chair poem for Rosemary and Keita for celebration, 2001 (Box 10)
    - Unquiet Grave, July 2001 (Box 10)
    - Copies of Cut up Material for Unquiet Grave (Box 10)
    - Pathetic attempts to write, fall 2001 in Buffalo (Box 10)
    - Summer, 2001 (Box 10)
    - French translation of "Thorow" [by Bernard Rival], 2002 (Box 10)
      Includes manuscript note from the translator, as well as a book mockup.
    - "Juliana / Anthology" regarding American Women Poets in the 21st Century, 2002 (Box 10)
      Includes correspondence, page proofs, layout instructions and other documentation.
    - "Bed Brought out of Scotland", circa 2003; 5 (Box 10)
    - Uta Grosmann interview [with SH] Germany, 2003 (Box 10)
    - "Shell Cornice" or "Bone Lace," summer 2003 (Box 10)
    - Some of version sent to Irish anthology, 2003 (Box 10)
    - Interview - SH with OB[ ?], circa 2003 (Box 10)
    - Tom Gardner interview with SH, Jan. 2003 (Box 10)
    - New poems, 2004 (Box 10)
    - Summer, 2004 (Box 10)
    - Interview SH with Jennifer Dick, 2007 (Box 10)
    - Souls of the Labadie Tract - mockup, 2007 (Box 10)
    - Souls of the Labadie Tract and "Fragments of the Wedding Dress of Sarah Pierpont Edwards" - mailed to SH, 2007 (Box 10)
    - "Fragments of the Wedding Dress of Sarah Pierpont Edwards" - Roger's final version, June 2007 (?), circa 2007 (Box 10)
    - Work for Landorian Notes (Box 10)
    - An Exchange between Susan Howe, Joan Jonas, Jeanne Heuving, circa 2004 (Box 10)
    - "The End of Art", review by SH (Box 10)
    - American Academy Book Recommendations (Box 10)
    - "Heliopathy", published in Temblor magazine (Box 10)
    - "Bare Lists of Words", "Ether Either", "Sorting Facts" (Box 10)
    - Stuff, Poems Not Used Etc. (Box 10)
    - Rain Taxi Interview [Grant Jenkins - SH] (Box 10)
    - Where Should the Commander Be (Box 10)
    - Marginal Notes [(Michael Drayton, later Unknown Man)] (Box 10)
    - "Sorting Facts", article published in Beyond Document: Essays on Non-Fiction Film (Charles Warren, ed.) (Box 10)
    - Loose manuscripts (Box 10)
- Notebooks and Diaries, 1984-2007; Series III; (3 boxes)
  The material found within this subseries is organized chronologically.
  - Moleskin and sketchbook notebooks, 1995-2007; 13 (Box 11)
  - Spiral notebooks, 1984-2002; 25 (Box 12)
  - Spiral notebooks, 2002-2005; 4 (Box 13)
- Professional Papers, 1961-2007; Series IV; (4 boxes)
  The series consists of teaching material (including annotated books), seminars, research material, reviews of Susan Howe's books, scholarly writing on Susan Howe's work, and interviews with Susan Howe. Also included are an NEA application and information regarding permissions, jurying, travel, reading and awards.
  Files have been left in the order in which they were received by the library.
  File titles have been transcribed from the original folders.
  - Miscellaneous correspondence about readings, conferences, publishing, etc., 1990s-2000s; 2 (Box 14)
  - Other Activities (Box 14)
  - Academy of American Poets, 2000-2001 (Box 14)
  - Poetics Business OB (Box 14)
  - Poems in Contemp. Lit. (Box 14)
  - Foreign Trips, 2000 (Box 14)
  - Stanford and Letters of Recommendation, 1998 (Box 14)
  - Votes for future classes (Box 14)
  - Sweden (Box 14)
  - Official letters / official papers, 1996-1997 (Box 14)
  - Publishers, contracts, etc., 1980s; 3 (Box 14)
  - Annotated books used in teaching
    - Billy Bud, Sailor, by Herman Melville, University of Chicago Press, 1962 (Box 14)
    - The Scarlet Letter, by Nathaniel Hawthrone, Houghton Mifflin Company, 1961 (Box 14)
    - Moby-Dick, by Herman Melville, Penguin Classics (Box 14)
    - The Master Letters of Emily Dickinson, edited by R.W. Franklin, Amherst College Press, 1986 (Box 14)
  - Creative Writing & Poetrty [sic], by Susan Howe, annotated course reader (Box 14)
  - Hinge Picture, book proof (Box 14)
  - General business - Ireland, 1999 (Box 14)
  - Buffalo Inaugeration, etc., 2004 (Box 14)
  - "Thorow" translation (Box 14)
  - Swedish Readings originals (Box 14)
  - Susan Howe / Nassjo (Box 14)
  - Swedish translation, 1999 (Box 14)
  - Spinnaker Swedish translation (Box 14)
  - Reading with Grubbs and Fourcade [?] at Cartier Paris, 2004 (Box 14)
  - Stevens lecture, 2001 (Box 14)
  - Philadelphia reading 2001: Pieces of the Midnight and Kidnapped (Box 14)
  - Emily Dickinson lecture [?] (Box 14)
  - Wallace Stevens Award, 2001 (Box 14)
  - Pierce Stuff, 2000 (Box 14)
  - Pierce Conference, 2002 (Box 14)
  - Chicago, 1998 (Box 14)
  - [John B.] Simpson Inaugeration - Buffalo (Box 14)
  - Saint Joseph College Commencement Ceremony, 2007 (Box 14)
  - Copy of Mills Lecture (Box 14)
  - Harvard and Cornell versions (Box 14)
  - Johns Hopkins Notes, 1997 (Box 14)
  - Notre Dame bits from 2nd lecture, 1997 (Box 14)
  - Dickinson slides for Wexner Center (Box 14)
  - Copy of 1st ND lecture (Box 14)
  - Talk for Mills (Box 14)
  - Possible quotes for MLA Talk, 1996 (Box 14)
  - Hart Crane Reading, 1999 (Box 14)
  - Buffalo- Pierce lecture (Box 14)
  - Pierce Lecture / Stanford (Box 14)
  - Houghton Permissions, 1998 (Box 15)
  - Current Reviews, etc., 2003-2004; 3 (Box 15)
  - Faculty Progress Report, 2005-2006 (Box 15)
  - Dickinson-Amherst Trip and Houghton, 1995 (Box 15)
  - Pound & Eliot: Poetry and War Seminar, 2005 (Box 15)
  - Olson Library Visit, 2005 (Box 15)
  - Hart Crane, photocopies (Box 15)
  - Longenbach visit - Notes for 4th seminar (Box 15)
  - Emerson / Poetry and Imagination (Box 15)
  - For 1st Seminar - Xerox (Box 15)
  - Society and Fidelity Claims - Stevens (Box 15)
  - Irresistible Dictation - Meyer (Box 15)
  - A History of American Funeral Directing (Box 15)
  - Olson / Melville / Dissertation Section (Box 15)
  - H.D. Life (Box 15)
  - American Primed (Box 15)
  - Week 4 (Box 15)
  - First Seminar - Buffalo, 2005 (Box 15)
  - Taylor, Edward and Psalms (Box 15)
  - Teresa Toulouse - Art of Prophesying (Box 15)
  - Prophetic Woman - Ann Hutchinson / Lang (Box 15)
  - Thomas Shepard / Autobiography (Box 15)
  - Ross J. Pudaloff - Witchcraft at Salem (Box 15)
  - Disorderly Women - Susan Juster (Box 15)
  - Ch. I Butler: The European Religious Heritage - Awash in a Sea (Box 15)
  - News From America / John Underhill (Box 15)
  - Pierce Material - MS 1190 (Box 15)
  - Pierce Chirography MS (Box 15)
  - MS 138 - Pierce (Box 15)
  - Pierce / Words (Box 15)
  - Pierce detail - book (Box 15)
  - MS 145 (Zemen) (Box 15)
  - Pierce editing accounts (Box 15)
  - MS 493 - Pierce material (Box 15)
  - MS 1537 - Pierce material (Box 15)
  - Material for Faculty Accomplishment Report (Box 15)
  - W. Stevens Library Research and Readers material (Box 15)
  - Milwaukee (Box 15)
  - Elisabeth Joyce - Thorowly American (Box 15)
  - Asparkia: Investigacio Feminista (Box 15)
  - As In Every Deafness - Graham Foust (Box 15)
  - A Reading of Susan Howe - James Putnam (Box 15)
  - The Cambridge history of Literary Criticism - Marshall Brown (Box 15)
  - Susan Howe Interview, 2001 (Box 15)
  - National Endowment for the Arts (NEA) Application Guidelines, 1988 (Box 15)
  - Xerox Texts for Susan Howe's Seminar: English 626 (Box 16)
  - Forest Lawn, 1990s (Box 16)
  - Vampire Material (Box 16)
  - Gertrude Stein - 'What is English Literature' (Box 16)
  - Charter 2006 - French Translation (Box 16)
  - Deluze / Kafka: Toward a Minor Literature (Box 16)
  - Higginson - Notes [Letter] to a Young Contributor (Box 16)
  - Ideas and Forms in Literature (Box 16)
  - Early American Narratives, bound photocopies (Box 16)
  - The Question of our Speech (Box 16)
  - Caspen paybacks (reimbursements, etc.), 2005 (Box 16)
  - Princeton lease and job letter, 2005 (Box 16)
  - Princeton and Spring Business, 2006 (Box 16)
  - Princeton correspondence, 2005 (Box 16)
  - Business - Caspen Fall 2005 (Box 16)
  - Princeton: Books, 2006 (Box 16)
  - Princeton stuff? (Box 16)
  - To Fill A Gap - Martha Nell Smith (Box 16)
  - Relevant Dickinson xerox material (Box 16)
  - Dickinson material / war material (Box 16)
  - Edwards - including [Wallace] Stevens, River of Rivers (Box 16)
  - Main Packet 308 (Box 16)
  - Week 3 (Box 16)
  - Mangan and Melville / Mitchel Harvard xerox (Box 16)
  - Course Packet 2: English #389, spring semester, 1996 (Box 16)
  - Business (Box 16)
  - Melville xeroxes (Box 16)
  - Fascicles #9 and 34, Class 5 (Box 16)
  - Sexuality and Space (Box 16)
  - Alice James Seminar '98, 1998 (Box 16)
  - Student, 2001 (Box 16)
  - Orals work, 2000 (Box 16)
  - Vertigo, added 1994 (Box 16)
  - Three Essays in Archaism - Stewart (Box 16)
  - The Architectural Notebook of Thomas Hardy (Box 16)
  - School work, 2000 (Box 16)
  - Seanee Stuff [?] (Box 16)
  - Transgression and Monstrosity, Poe 1 and 2, 1994 (Box 16)
  - Transgression and Monstrosity, Poe 1 / William Wilson and Ligeia (Box 16)
  - William Wilson - Poe #2 (Box 16)
  - Mosses / on Hawthorne, Melville - Crane on M[elville] and Stein III (Box 16)
  - Undergrad 3rd Weeks Primer (Box 16)
  - Cover material? Embalmers book - History of American Funeral Directing (Box 16)
  - Goblin Market and Dracula (Box 16)
  - Transgression and Monstrosity 1994 #1 outline and Ballads of purpose (Box 16)
  - The Ancient Mariner folder [empty] (Box 16)
  - 1st Class - Transgression and Monstrosity (Box 16)
  - T[ransgression] and M[onstrosity] 94 - Exams and Questions etc. Essays, 1994 (Box 16)
  - Trans[gression] and M[onstrosity] - H. James II-2 (Box 16)
  - Library material (Box 16)
  - #625 5th Seminar (Box 16)
  - Dickinson editing (Box 16)
  - Dickinson / Shelley Seminar 1992 (Box 16)
  - T[ransgression] and M[onstrosity] Bronte: #1 (Box 16)
  - Bronte #2 - Telepathy, Cryptography / Royle (Box 16)
  - Bronte 3: Telepathy (Box 16)
  - The Rime of the Ancient Mariner: A Handbook, Royal A. Gettman, photocopy (Box 16)
  - T[ransgression] and M[onstrosity]: 2 Coleridge, 1992 (Box 16)
  - T[ransgression] and M[onstrosity] 1994 Coleridge (Box 16)
  - Coleridge - The Ancient Mariner, 3rd Lecture. (Box 16)
  - Coleridge 4th lecture (Box 16)
  - 2nd Seminar Melville (Box 16)
  - Melville / Bartleby #625 (Box 16)
  - Transgression and Monstrosity - Benito Cereno, Melville 2 (Box 16)
  - Last Melville class, undergraduate - Bartleby (Box 16)
  - Transgression and Monstrosity - Melville 1 (Box 16)
  - Transgression and Monstrosity: Melville, Benito Cereno 1 (Box 16)
  - 1994 Seminar: Dickinson (Box 16)
  - Hart Crane things for Seminar, folder [empty] (Box 16)
  - T[ransgression] and M[onstrosity] 5th lecture '92 fall: Mary Shelley, 1992 (Box 16)
  - Mary Shelley's life - seminar 1994 (Box 16)
  - Framing / Frankenstein (Box 16)
  - Mary Shelley 2. Monster / T[ransgression] and M[onstrosity] 6 (Box 16)
  - T[ransgression] and M[onstrosity]: M. Shelley - 7 and 8 #7 (Box 16)
  - Mary Shelley - last (Box 16)
  - T[ransgression] and M[onstrosity]: M. Shelley 2 (Box 16)
  - Spring 2004 Graduate course descriptions (Box 17)
  - Dracula 2 and Vertigo, added 1994 (Box 17)
  - Book lists - Dickinson and H.D. (Box 17)
  - Notes for both Graduate and Undergraduate (Box 17)
  - 1st Lecture 2003 - Books (Box 17)
  - 2nd Lecture 2003 - Extract and Etym. (Box 17)
  - 3rd Lecture Sermon (Box 17)
  - 4th Lecture 2003 (Box 17)
  - Library material 2003 (Box 17)
  - Early New England poetry (Box 17)
  - [Aaron] Fogal essay on Prose (Box 17)
  - Library lists, 1991-1992 (Box 17)
  - Casamassima, 1998 (Box 17)
  - Altar and Corner 1 (Box 17)
  - Golden Bowl - Henry James (Box 17)
  - [Henry] James seminar (Box 17)
  - 2nd Seminar - My first lecture - Buffalo, 1998 (Box 17)
  - The Golden Bowl - Henry James / Sex and Space - final seminar (Box 17)
  - Buffalo, 1998 (Box 17)
  - Casamassima, 1998 (Box 17)
  - 2nd Week - James (Box 17)
  - Altar 2 and Corner (Box 17)
  - 1st Seminar (Box 17)
  - 1st seminar 05 - War and Poetry (Box 17)
  - First Class intro - i.e. Narratives, start of Shepard idea (Box 17)
  - Teresa Toulouse (Box 17)
  - Ann Kibbey (Box 17)
  - 2nd Seminar (Box 17)
  - Sex and Space - Henry James, Turn of the Screw (Box 17)
  - Transgression and Monstrosity - Henry James (Box 17)
  - Life of E[mily] D[ickenson] / Sewell / Holland (Box 17)
  - E.D. Fragments and First Class (Box 17)
  - Print art and interview (Box 17)
  - Dracula, 1997 (Box 17)
- Personal and Family Papers, circa 1916-2001; Series V; (3 boxes)
  The series consists of family papers remaining after the death of Howe's mother including photographs, documents, and letters (with several written by Howe) as well as a photocopy typescript of an autobiographical work written by Howe's mother, which, among other things, deals with the Poet's Theater in Boston. Also included are printouts of email correspondence between Howe and her late husband Peter Hare, November 1999 – March 2001, and photographs and other material relating to her late husband David von Schlegell.
  - Ma's Last Calendar, circa 1999 (Box 18)
    Includes a pocket address book, a older photograph of George Gilmore, two U.S. Passports for Mary Manning Adams and a 1999 wall calendar entitled "The Personal Photo Calendar: Exclusively Designed for You."
  - Ma and Me, photograph (Box 18)
  - Uncle John's burial (Box 18)
  - Letter from Dublin / Ma and Beckett (Box 18)
  - David von Schlegell sculpture during the time we were together 1965-1992, photographs (Box 18)
  - David's Death - Dr. etc., 1992 (Box 18)
    Includes a U.S. Passport for Susan (née Howe) von Schlegell.
  - David's studio at the time of his death, 1992 (Box 18)
  - Photograph Album, circa 1916 (Box 18)
  - Susan Howe - Peter Hewitt Hare correspondence, 1999-2001; 16 (Box 19)
  - Mary Howe Adams papers, 2 (Box 19)
    Includes loose family photographs, a framed photograph of "Uncle" Johnny Ames (circa 1940s), and newspaper clippings.
  - Mary Howe Adams papers correspondence, 1983, 1994-1996, undated; 3 (Box 19)
  - Mary Howe Adams, photographs, 2 (Box 19)
    Includes various family photographs, as well as two framed photographs.
  - Mary Howe Adams, other papers (Box 19)
  - Mother's Death - 1999 (Box 19)
  - Uncle John's Beckett letters - sold to St. Louis (Box 19)
  - Material connected to Mary Manning and Susan Howe, 1938 (Box 19)
  - Louise Bennett - My Great Aunt, circa 1955 (Box 19)
  - Letters from Polly and Us / to Mary Manning (Ma) (Box 19)
  - Some Family stuff - Letters, Aunt Helen's Obituary, etc., 1950s-1970s (Box 19)
  - Ashleat Cartoon - 1955: Perry, Lavinia, Nora and Me., circa 1955 (Box 19)
  - Daddy's military service [Mark DeWolfe Howe], circa 1945 (Box 19)
  - Draft of book, "Molly", 4 (Box 19)
  - Family photograph album, 1920s-1950s (Box 20 (Oversize))
- Art Work, circa 1959-early 1980s; Series VI; (1 box) + 9 broadside folders
  - Artist's Book, circa 1971-1973 (Box 21 (Oversize))
    Untitled, handmade artist's/poet's book including original drawing, painting, collage, and text.
  - Drawings, circa 1959-early 1980s
    In-process material. As of January, 2019, this collection is closed to readers temporarily, and will reopen when conservation treatment is complete.
    Arranged into eight groups by the artist.
    Drawings and word drawings by Susan Howe, watercolor, collage, graphite, and pen-and-ink, chiefly made in Ireland and New York in the 1970s and 1980s. Also includes a drawing by Howe of a hotel interior, Achill Island, Ireland, in 1959; two drawings by Jonathan Shahn, of Howe and Henry Geldzahler, circa 1960; and a cover design by and poster for an exhibit of David von Schlegell.
    - Untitled group, Late 1970s-early 1980s; 6
    - Untitled group, Early to mid 1970s; 18
    - "Birds, Dalkey Ireland", 1971-1972; 16
    - "Garden Charts", early 1980s; 6
    - Untitled group, 1959-1976, undated; 6
    - Untitled group, Undated; 8
    - "Odd ones, no particular order", Undated; 7